UTU Audio-Visual Material 5139 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
UTU Audio-Visual Material
1958-1975
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
United Transportation Union (UTU)
5139 AV
9.22 cubic feet
9.2 linear ft.
Audiovisual materials.
The United Transportation Union (UTU) Audiovisual Materials Collection consists of video taped union activities; meetings; information videos; employee assistant videos and miscellaneous videos of activities.
7581764
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 17, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The United Transportation Union (UTU) is headquartered in Cleveland, Ohio. It is a broad-based, transportation labor union representing about 125,000 active and retired railroad, bus, mass transit, and airline workers in the United States.
In 1968 four brotherhoods' became interested in joining together to make one transporatation union, the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen and the Switchmen's Union of North America. The new union was to be called the United Transportation Union and came into existence on January 1, 1969, after an overwhelming vote of the 4 unions on December 10, 1968, in Chicago.
The first president was Charles Luna, formerly president of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and had 230,000 members. The International Association of Railway Employees joined in 1970. The Railroad Yardmasters of America joined the union in 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5139: UTU Records 5139 MB: UTU Memorabilia 5139 P: UTU Photographs 6055: UTU Additional Collective Bargaining Agreements 6023: UTU Additional Records 5164: UTU Canada Records 5622: UTU New York State Legislative Board Selected Files 5711: UTU New York State Legislative Director Files 5589: UTU Vice-President's Office George W. Legg Subject Files 5501 AV: UTU. Young Leadership Conference Audio recordings 5196: UTU Ladies' Auxiliary Iowa Joint Board Minutes
Transport workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Wages -- Transport workers-- United States; United Transportation Union
7581764
- UTU Meeting - 9/13/1985 in Jackson Hole, Wyoming, 5 (Box 35)
  Scope and Contents
  These VHS tapes were found in boxes, 53, 54, 56 of 5139, and transferred here
- Operation Red Block, 1 (Box 28)
- Mr. W. Hirst, Int'l. VP BLE Accountability and Action from viewpoint of Union: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 29)
- Mr. W. Williamson, Director Research & Education Dept. BRAC From viewpoint of Union: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 30)
- Mr. C.E. O'Hara, Asst. V.P. "Accountability and Action" viewpoint of management: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 31)
- Mr. Herrel Bird & J. Dargon Closing remarks: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 32)
- Mr. D. Sorenson - Director Employe Assistance Program UP "Action-Brothers": removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 33)
- Introduction Jim Dargon; Speaker Herrol Bird: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 34)
- Operation Red Block, 1 (Box 35)
- Choose UTU 9/13/1988, 2 (Box 35)
  These VHS tapes were found in boxes, 53, 54, 56 of 5139, and transferred here`
- New Technologies - Old Fashioned Solidarity / Elements of a successful United Pilots Strike / Air Line Pilots Association, 4 (Box 36)
  pulled from 5139/box84
- United Transportation Union - One Direction: ForwardOne Future: Solid Choose UTU, 4 (Box 35)
- Mr. D. Brake, Director Planning & Program Development Secy., & Spec. Serv. UP RR: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 25)
- Yes You Can, So You Can: Training Video, 6 (Box 35)
- Rail Views, 8 (Box 35)
- Tom Breen, Alcoholic Program, May, 1978 - Thunder Bay, Ontario, 1 (Box 43)
  pulled from 5139/box 109
- Labor History, 10 (Box 35)
- Movin' On, 11 (Box 35)
- Operation Red Block, 12 (Box 35)
- United Transportation Union - One Direction: ForwardOne Future: SolidChoose UTU, 13 (Box 35)
- Parliamentary Procedures, 1 (Box 36)
  pulled from 5139/box 82
- Buck Trent - Promo, 2 (Box 36)
  pulled from 5139/box82
- Labor video bulletin - #22-A, 3 (Box 36)
  pulled from 5139/box 84
- United Transportation Union - One Direction: ForwardOne Future: Solid - Choose UTU, 3 (Box 35)
- Mr. D. Brake, Director Planning & Program Development Secy., & Spec. Serv. UP RR: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 15)
- Mr. R.E. Boswell, Pres., Kansas Peace Officers Assn. Scy. &; Spec.: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 3)
- Introduction Jim Dargon; Speaker Herrol Bird: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 4)
- J. Dragon, Jr., (Bypass); bill Gossert NTSM; Dargon re: UP rule G Bypass: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 5)
- Mr. D. Sorenson - Director Employe Assistance Program UP "Action-Brothers": removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 6)
- Jack Haley: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 7)
- Mr. W. Hirst, Int'l. VP BLE Accountability and Action from viewpoint of Union: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 8)
- Mr. G.P. Burns, Dir. Of Safety UP RR "Action-Results": removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 9)
- Mr. C.E. O'Hara, Asst. V.P. "Accountability and Action" - Viewpoint of Management: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 10)
- Mr. D. Brake, Directory Planning & Program Development Secy. & Spec. Serv. UP RR: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 11)
- Mr. W. Williamson, Director Research & Education Dept. BRAC from viewpoint of Union: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 12)
- Mr. D. Brake, Director Planning & Program Development Secy. & Spec. Serv. UP RR: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 27)
- Mr. Herrel Bird & J. Dargon Closing remarks: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 14)
- Mr. D. Collins, Sr., Asst. Gen. Secy. & Treas., UTU; from viewpoint of Union: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 26)
- J. Dargon - CSX - 1984 - Huntington WVA: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 16)
- Mr. R.E. Boswell, Pres., Kansas Peace Officers Assn. Secy. & Spec.: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 17)
- Mr. D. Collins, Sr., Asst. Gen. Secy. & Treas., UTU - From viewpoint of Union: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 18)
- Mr. D. Brake, Director Planning & Program Development Secy. & Spec. Serv. UP RR: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 19)
- Railroads: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 20)
- Mr. G.P. Burns, Dir. Of Safety Union Pacific Railroad - "Action-Results": removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 21)
- Mr. R.E. Boswell, Pres., Kansas Peace Officers Assn. Secy. & Spec.: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 22)
- Mr. G.P. Gurns, Dir. Of Safety UP RR "Action-Results": removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 23)
- J. Dargon, Jr., (Bypass); Bill Gossert NTSB; Dargon re: UP rule G Bypass: removed from box 56/5139, 1 (Box 24)
- Railroading: A Way of Life, 9 (Box 35)
- Jack Hailey: removed from box 54/5139, 1 (Box 13)
- Day 2, 1 (Box 41)
  pulled from 5139/box 75
- Davids Run, 11 (Box 37)
  pulled from 5139/box 81
- Teamsters on the air VNR: June 24-28, 1991, 12 (Box 37)
- Singing for the union, 13 (Box 37)
- Unlabeled, 14 (Box 37)
- Mr. Don Levine, Acting Chief of Rail Vehicles, 15 (Box 37)
- Train-to-train Impact tests - Phase I, 16 (Box 37)
- UTU Audition, Mike Kraft, Quaker State, 5 (Box 36)
- Tour of the turbo, 20 (Box 36)
  pulled from 5139/box 78
- K-4 Train: David Hoover --- 4/29/1987, 7 (Box 35)
- Jim Dargon to Dan Collins - Prevention Committee Function - 12/3/1986, 1 (Box 38)
  pulled from 5139/box78
- Hyatt Regency Chicago Hotel, 10 (Box 37)
- Wed. 6/13 - 3rd day, 1 (Box 40)
  pulled from 5139/box75
- Hazardous Material tank car fire studies, 17 (Box 37)
- Day 2, 1 (Box 41)
- John Aries Film, 1 (Box 42)
  5-1/2" open reel -- pulled from 5139-box 102
- Anderson: "Coal Connection" Head, 2 (Box 42)
  9-1/4" open reel -- pulled from 5139/bx 102
- Fight For My Union, 3 (Box 42)
- The Real Issue, the Phony Issue, 4 (Box 42)
- It's Time to Say YES to Dukakis, 5 (Box 42)
  pulled from 5139/bx98
- Union Pacific System: Operation Red Block-Making Rule G Work: LR-55-65, 6 (Box 42)
  pulled from 5139/bx97
- C-Span talk show featuring Karen Ball, Labor Writer for the Associated Press with telephone call-ins regarding the April 17, 1991 nation wide rail strike, 7 (Box 42)
  pulled from 5139/box 119
- Amalgamation / H.E. Gilbert: 3/15/1958, 8 (Box 42)
- Your Life Your Money - 1/23/1958, 9 (Box 42)
- Ramona Belford, Okmulgee, OK - Al-Anon Talk, Tyler Texas 6/2/1972, 1 (Box 39)
- The Mullet Bay Resort & Casino, 9 (Box 36)
- One Strike and You're Out! / Committee for Workplace Fairness, 6 (Box 36)
- Reuther - Face the Nation, 21 (Box 36)
- Highlights of 1989 AFL-CIO Convention, 8 (Box 36)
- Glenn Colerider Demo Tape, 9 (Box 37)
- AFL-CIO COPE - The Margin of Victory, 10 (Box 36)
- We Take Care of Our Own: Missouri Pacific Employee's Health Association, 11 (Box 36)
- Labor Bulletin - #27-B, 12 (Box 36)
- 2nd Quarter 1991 / CSX Transportation Video News, Transportation Dept., 13 (Box 36)
- Labor Video Bulletin - #24, 14 (Box 36)
- First Quarter - 1988, 15 (Box 36)
- Westin Bonaventure Marketing Video, 16 (Box 36)
- Labor Institute of Public Affairs/AFL-CIO - Solidarity Day '91, 1991; 17 (Box 36)
- President Hardin's Speech before the AT & SF, General Committee in Overland Park, Kansas on January 26, 1987, 18 (Box 36)
- Roberts - Rules of Order, 19 (Box 36)
- Labor Video Bulletin - #28-B, 1 (Box 37)
- Higher Profits Versus Public Safety // Save the Caboose, 2 (Box 37)
- Unlabeled, 3 (Box 37)
- Library History Rediscovered, 4 (Box 37)
- Labor video bulletin - #26, 5 (Box 37)
- Metropolitan Life Insurance Company "On the question of taxing employer provided benefits", 6 (Box 37)
- Trains Safer w/Caboose, 7 (Box 37)
- Labor video bulletin #20, 8 (Box 37)
- Working in the USA: Know Your Rights - English and Spanish, 7 (Box 36)
- Train to train impact test: Test 9, 1975; 1 (Box 1)
  May 30, 1975; TTC, Pueblo, Colorado
- Train to Train Impact Test: Test 9, 1975; 1 (Box 1)
- Roll 2; Sonochrome 7252, 2 (Box 1)
- CAM 2, 3 (Box 1)
- CAM 4, 4 (Box 1)
- CAM 1, 5 (Box 1)
- Train to Train Impact Test: Test No. 9, 1975; 6 (Box 1)
- Unlabeled, 7 (Box 1)
- ROL - CAM, 8 (Box 1)
- CAM 3, 9 (Box 1)
- Unlabeled, 10 (Box 1)
- Unlabeled, 11 (Box 1)
- Interview by Bob Julian of Dan W. Collins, Asst. General Secretary Treasurer of the United Transportation Union, 1969; 12 (Box 1)
  3/6/1969
- Accidents without Firemen on M.E.R.R., 1966; 13 (Box 1)
  March 24, 1966; February 6, 1966
- Amalgamation - H.E. Gilbert, 1958; 14 (Box 1)
  3/15/1958
- Tape of crossing accident May 19, 1966; Tape of Engineer being attacked on locomotive by Charles Mason, M.E.R.R., July 7, 1966, 15 (Box 1)
- Festival - American Folk life - Washington, D.C.: June 1975, 16 (Box 1)
  19 slides
- Vice-President Kenneth Levin "Section 6 notices", 1 (Box 2)